this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
today I'm talking to Luca casanado he's
a member of the dino core team and a
tc39 delegate Luca welcome to software
engineering radio hey thanks for having
me so today we're going to talk about
Dino and on the website it says Dino is
a runtime for JavaScript and typescript
so I thought we could start with
defining what a runtime is yeah that's a
great question I think this question
actually comes up a lot it's like
sometimes we also Define Dino as a
headless browser or I don't know a
JavaScript execution tool what actually
defines a runtime I think
what makes a runtime of runtime is that
it is a it's implemented in native code
it cannot be self-hosted like you cannot
self-host a JavaScript runtime
and it executes JavaScript or typescript
or some other scripting language
without relying on well yeah I guess
it's the self-hosting thing like it's
essentially a JavaScript execution
engine which is not self-hosted
so yeah it maybe has i o bindings but it
doesn't necessarily need to like it
maybe it allows you to read from the
file system or or make Network calls but
it doesn't necessarily have to it's I
think the the primary definition is
something which can execute JavaScript
without already being written in
JavaScript and when we hear about
JavaScript runtimes whether it's Dino or
node or bun or anything else we also
hear about it in the context of V8 could
you explain the relationship between V8
and a JavaScript runtime yeah so V8 and
JavaScript core and the spider monkey
these are all JavaScript engines so
these are the low level virtual machines
that can execute or that can parse your
JavaScript code turn it into byte code
maybe turn it into compiled machine code
and then execute that code but these
engines do not Implement any i o
functions they implement the JavaScript
spec as is written
and then they provide extension hooks
for they call these host environments um
like environments that embed these
engines to provide custom
functionalities to essentially poke out
of the sandbox out of the virtual
machine and this is used in browsers
like browsers have have these engines
built in this is where they originated
from and then they poke holes into this
sandbox virtual machine to do things
like I don't know writing to the Dom or
console logging or making fetch calls
and all these kinds of things and what a
runtime essentially does a JavaScript
runtime is it takes one of these engines
and it then provides its own set of host
apis like essentially its own set of
holes it pokes into the sandbox and
depending on what the runtime is trying
to do the way it will do this is going
to be different and the sort of API that
is ultimately exposed to the end user is
going to be different for example if you
compare Dino node like node is very
loosey-goosey but how it pokes holds it
to the sandbox it sort of just pokes
them everywhere and this makes it
difficult to enforce things like runtime
permissions for example whereas Dino is
much more strict about how it pokes
holds into its sandbox like everything
is either a web API or it's behind in
this Dino name space which means that
it's it's really easy to find places
where you're poking out of the sandbox
and really you can also compare these to
browsers like browsers also JavaScript
runtimes um they're just not headless
JavaScript runtimes but JavaScript
runtimes that also have a UI and yeah
there's a whole bunch of different kinds
of JavaScript runtimes and I think we're
also seeing a lot more like embedded
JavaScript runtimes like for example if
you've used react native before you may
be using Hermes as a JavaScript engine
in your Android app which is like a
custom JavaScript engine written just
for for react native
and this also is embedded within a like
react native runtime which is specific
to react native so it's also possible to
have runtimes for example that can be
where the backing engine can be
exchanged which is kind of cool so it
sounds like Waits role one way to look
at it is it can execute JavaScript code
but only
pure functions I suppose you can pretty
much yeah
do anything that doesn't interact with i
o so you think about browsers you were
mentioning you need to interact with the
Dom or if you're writing a server-side
application you probably need to receive
or make HTTP requests that sort of thing
all of that is not handled by V8 that
has to be handled by an external runtime
exactly there's like some exceptions to
this for example JavaScript technically
has some i o built in within its
standard Library like math.random
it's like random number generation is
technically an i o operation so
technically V8 has some i o built in
right and like getting the current date
from the user that's also technically I
O so there's some very limited edge
cases it's it's not that it's purely
pure but V8 for example has a flag to
turn it completely deterministic which
means that it really is completely pure
and this is not something which run
times usually have this is something
like the feature of an engine because
the engine is like so low level that it
can essentially there's so little i o
that it's very easy to make
deterministic or a runtime higher level
has i o much more difficult to make
deterministic and for things like when
you're working with JavaScript there's
uh asynchronous programming and so you
have concurrency and things like that is
that a part of V8 or is that the
responsibility of the runtime
that's a good question so there's
multiple parts to this there's the part
there's JavaScript promises and sort of
concurrent JavaScript execution which is
sort of handled by V8 like V8 you can in
pure via you can create a promise and
you can
execute some code within that promise
but without IO there's actually no way
to defer time which means that with pure
V8 you can either you can create a
promise which executes right now or you
can create a promise that never executes
but you can't create a promise that
executes in 10 seconds because there's
no way to measure 10 seconds
asynchronously what runtimes do is they
add something called an event loop on
top of this on top of the base engine
and that event Loop for example like a
very simple event Loop for example might
have a timer in it which every second
looks at if there's a timer scheduled to
run within that second and if it does if
that timer exists it'll go call out to
V8 and say you can now execute that
promise
but V8 is still the one that's keeping
track of like which promises exist and
the code that is meant to be invoked
when they resolve all that kind of thing
but the underlying infrastructure that
actually invokes which promises get
resolved at what point in time like the
asynchronous i o is what this is called
this is driven by the event Loop which
is implemented by a runtime
so Dino for example it uses Tokyo for
its event Loop this is a event Loop
written in Rust it's very popular in the
rust ecosystem node uses libuv this is a
relatively popular runtime event Loop
implementation for C plus plus and libuv
was written for node Tokyo was not
written for Dino but yeah Chrome has its
own event Loop implementation button has
its own event Loop implementation we
might go a little bit more into that
later but I think
what we should probably go into now is
why make Dino because you have node
that's currently very popular
the co-creator of Dino to my
understanding actually created node
so maybe you could explain to our
audience what was missing or what was
wrong with node where they decided I
need to create a new runtime yeah so the
primary point of concern here was that
node was slowly diverging from browser
standards with no real path to
reconverging like there was nothing that
was pushing node in the direction of
Standards compliance and there was
nothing that was
like sort of forcing node to innovate
and we really saw this because in the
time between I don't know
2050 and 2018 like node was slowly
working on esm while browsers had
already shipped esm for like three years
node did not have fetch node only got
fetch last year right six seven years
after browsers got fetched
nodes stream implementation is still
very Divergent from standard web streams
node was very reliant on callbacks it
still is like promises in many places of
the node API are an afterthought which
makes sense because node was created in
a time before promises existed but there
was really nothing that was pushing node
forward right like nobody was actively
investing in improving the API of node
to be more standards compliant
and so what we really needed was a new
like Greenfield project which could
demonstrate that actually writing a new
server-side runtime is a viable and B is
totally doable with an API that is more
standards compliant like essentially you
can write a browser like a headless
browser and have that be
an excellent to use JavaScript runtime
right and then there were some things
that were added on top of that like a
typescript support because typescript
was incredibly or is still incredibly
popular even more so than it was four
years ago when Dino was created or
envisioned this permission system like
node really poked holes into the V8
sandbox very early on with like it's
going to be very difficult for node to
ever reconcile this
especially because of the sum of the
apis that it exposes are just so
incredibly low level that like I don't
know you can mutate random memory within
your process which like if you want to
have a secure sandbox like that just
doesn't work not compatible
so there was it really needed to be a
place where you could explore this
direction and see if it worked and
dinner was that do you know it still is
that and I think Dino has outgrown that
now into something which is much more
usable as like a production ready
runtime and many people do use it in
production and now dino is on the path
of slowly converging back with node from
both directions like node is slowly
becoming more standards compliant and
depending on who you ask this was this
was done because of Dino and some people
said it would had already been going on
and you know just accelerated it
but that's not really relevant because
the point is that like note is becoming
more standards compliant and and the
other direction is Dino is becoming more
node compliant like Dino is implementing
node compatibility layers that allow you
to run code that was originally written
for the node ecosystem in the standards
compliant runtime
so through those two directions the
runtimes are sort of going back towards
each other I don't think they'll ever
merge but we're getting to a point here
pretty soon I think where it doesn't
really matter what run time you write
for because you'll be able to write code
written for one runtime in the other
runtime relatively easily so if you're
saying the two are
becoming closer to one another becoming
closer to the web standard that runs in
the browser if you're talking to someone
who's currently developing in node
what's the incentive for them to switch
to dino versus continued using node and
then hope that eventually they'll kind
of meet in the middle
yeah so I think like Dino is a lot more
than just around time right like a
runtime executes JavaScript you know
executes JavaScript it executes
typescript but Dino is so much more than
that like Dino has a built-in formatter
it has a built-in linter it has a
built-in testing framework a built-in
benching framework it has built-in
bundler it like can create self-hosted
executables yeah like bundle your code
and the dino executable into a single
executable that you can ship off to
someone it has a dependency analyzer it
has editor Integrations it has like I
could go on for hours about all of the
auxiliary tooling that's inside of Dino
that's not a JavaScript runtime and also
do you know as a JavaScript runtime is
just more standards compliant than any
of the other server-side runtimes right
now so if you're really looking for
something which is standards compliant
which is going to like live on forever
then it's you know like you cannot kill
off the fetch API ever the fetch API is
going to live forever because Chrome
supports it and the same goes for local
storage and and like I don't know the
blob API and all these other web apis
like they have shipped in browsers which
means that they will be supported until
the end of time
yeah maybe node has also reached that
with its API probably to some extent but
yeah don't underestimate the power of
like three billion Chrome users that
would scream immediately if the fetch
API stopped working right yeah I think
maybe what it sounds like also is that
because you're using the API that's used
in the browser
places where you deploy JavaScript
applications in the future you would
hope that those would all settle on
using that same API so that if you were
using Dino you could host it at
different places and not worry about
do I need to use a special
API like maybe that you would in node
yeah exactly and this is actually
something which we're specifically
working towards so I don't know if
you've heard of winter CG it's a
community group with the w3c that
cloudflare and Andino and some others
including Shopify have started last year
where essentially we're trying to
standardize the concept of what a
server-side JavaScript runtime is and
what apis it needs to have available to
be standards compliant and essentially
making this portability sort of written
down somewhere and like write down
exactly what code you can write and
expect to be portable and we can see
like that all the big players that are
involved in building JavaScript runtimes
right now are actively engaged with us
at wintry CG and are actively building
towards this future so I would expect
that any code that you write today which
runs
pandino runs in cloudflare workers runs
on netlify edge functions runs on for
sale at runtime runs on Shopify oxygen
is going to run on the other four of
those within the next couple years here
like I think the apis of these are just
going to converge to be essentially the
same which is obviously going to always
be some some nuances like I don't know
Chrome and Firefox and Safari don't
perfectly have the same API everywhere
right like Chrome has some web Bluetooth
capabilities that Safari doesn't or
Firefox has some I don't know
non-standard extensions the error object
which none of the other runtimes do but
overall you can expect these runtimes to
mostly be aligned
and I think that's really really
excellent and that's I think really one
of the reasons why one should really
consider building for this standard
runtime because it just guarantees that
you'll be able to host this somewhere in
five years time in 10 years time with
very little effort like even if Dino
goes under or cloudflare goes under or
I don't know nobody decides to maintain
node anymore
it'll be easy to run somewhere else
and also I expect that the big cloud
vendors will ultimately provide managed
offerings for the standards compliant
JavaScript runtime as well and this
winter CG group is node a part of that
as well yes we've invited node to join
due to the complexities of how nodes
internal decision making system works
node is not officially a member of
winter CG there's some individual
members of the north technical steering
committee which are participating for
example James M Snell is my co-chair on
winter CG he also works at
cloudflipperty's also a node TSC member
Matteo Colina who's been instrumental to
getting fetch landed in node is also
actively involved so the node is
involved but
because node is node and and node's
decision making process works the way it
does node is not officially listed
anywhere as a member but yeah they're
involved and maybe they'll be a member
at some point but
yeah let's
see yeah so it sounds like you're
thinking that's more of a governance or
organizational aspect of node then it is
a technical limitation is that right
yeah like I obviously can't speak for
the node technical steering committee
but I know that there's a significant
chunk of the node technical steering
committee that is very favorable towards
standards compliance but parts of the no
technical stream committee also not they
are either indifferent or are actively I
don't know if they're still actively
working against this but have actively
worked against standards compliance in
the past
and because the node governance
structure is very is so open and Lets
All these voices be heard that just
means that decision making processes
within node can take so long like
this is also why the fetch API took
eight years to ship like this was not a
technical problem and it is also not a
technical problem that node does not
have URL pattern support or the file
Global or the web crypto API was not on
this on the global object until like
late last year right like these are not
technical problems these they're
decision-making problems
and yeah that was also part of the
reason why we started Dino as like a
separate thing because you can try to
innovate node from the inside but
innovating node from the inside is very
slow very tedious and
requires a lot of fighting and sometimes
just showing somebody from the outside
like look this is the bright future you
could have makes them more inclined to
do something do you have a sense for you
gave the example of fetch taking eight
years to to get into node do you have a
sense of what the typical objection is
to something like that like I understand
there's a lot of people involved but why
would somebody say I don't want this
yeah so for fetch specifically there was
many different kinds of concerns I can
maybe list two of them one of them was
for example that the fetch API is not a
good API and as such node did not have
it which
is sort of
missing the point of because it's a
standard API how good or bad the API is
is much less relevant because if you can
share the API you can also share a
wrapper that's written around the API
right and then the other concern was
node does need fetch because node
already has an HTTP API
so these are both kind of examples of
concerns that people had for a long time
which it took a long time to either
convince these people or or to push the
change through anyway
and this is also the case for other
things like for example web crypto why
do we need webcrypto we already have
node crypto or why do we need yet
another streams implementation node
already has four different streams
implementations like why do we need web
streams like I don't know if you know
this XKCD of there's 14 competing
standards so let's write a 15 standard
to unify them all and then at the end we
just have 15 competing standards so I
think this is also the kind of concern
that people were concerned about but I
think what we've seen here is that this
is really not a concern that one needs
to have because it ends up that or it
turns out in the end that if you
implement web apis people will use web
apis and will use web apis only for
their new code it takes a while but
we're seeing this with esm versus
required like new code written with
require
much less common than it was two years
ago and new code Now using like xhr
whatever it's called form request or you
know the one I mean compared to using
fetch like nobody uses that everybody
uses Fetch and like in node if you write
a little script like you're going to use
fetch you're not going to use like nodes
http.getapi or whatever
so yeah we're gonna see the same thing
with readable stream we're going to see
the same thing with webcrypto we're
going to see the same thing with blob
like I think one of the big ones were
known as
still I don't think this is one that's
ever going to get solved is the the
buffer Global in node like we have the
uint8 this unit 8 Global and like all
the runtimes including browsers and
buffer is like a superset of that but
it's in global scope so it's sort of
this non-standard extension of Unit 8
array that people in node like to use
and it's not compatible with anything
else but because it's so easy to get at
people use it anyway so those are also
kind of problems that that we'll have to
deal with eventually and maybe that
means that at some point the buffer
Global gets deprecated and I don't know
it probably can never get removed but
these are kinds of conversations that
the node TSC is going to have to have
internally in I don't know maybe five
years yeah so at a high level what's
shipped in the browser it went through
the ecmascript approval process
people got it into the browser once it's
in the browser probably never going away
and because of that it's safe to build
on top of that for these server runtimes
because
it's never going away from the browser
and so everybody can kind of use it into
the future and not worry about it yeah
exactly yeah and that's excluding the
benefit that also if you have code that
you can write once and use in both the
browser and the server side runtime like
that's really nice that's the other
benefit yeah I think that's really
powerful in that right now when
someone's looking at running something
in cloudflare workers versus running
something in the browser versus running
something in node
it's I think a lot of people make the
Assumption it's just JavaScript so I can
use it as is but it there are at least
currently differences in what apis are
available to you
earlier you were talking about how Dino
is more than just the runtime it has
linter formatter file Watcher there's
all sorts of stuff in there and I wonder
if you could talk a little bit to the
reasoning behind that versus
having them all be separate things
yeah so the reasoning here is
essentially if you look at other modern
languages like rust is a great example
go is a great example even though go was
designed around the same time as node it
has a lot of these same tools built in
and what it really shows is that if the
ecosystem converges is essentially
forced to converge on a single set of
built-in tooling a that built-in tooling
becomes really really excellent because
everybody's using it
and also it means that if you open any
project written by any go developer any
any rust developer and you look at the
tests you immediately understand how the
test framework works and you immediately
understand how the assertions work and
you immediately understand how the build
system works and you immediately
understand how the dependency Imports
work and you immediately understand like
I want to run this project and I want to
restart it when my file changes like you
immediately know how to do that because
it's the same everywhere and this kind
of feeling of having to learn one tool
and then being able to use all of the
projects like being able to contribute
to open source when you're moving jobs
whatever like between personal projects
that you haven't touched in two years
you know being able to learn this once
and then use it everywhere such an
incredibly powerful tool like people
don't appreciate this until they've used
a runtime or language which provides
this to them like you can go to any go
developer and ask them if they would
like there's this saying in the go
ecosystem that go fmt is nobody's
favorite
but oh wait no I don't remember how the
saying goes but the saying essentially
implies that the way that go fmt formats
code maybe not everybody likes but
everybody loves go fmt anyway because it
just makes everything look the same and
like you can read your friend's code
your colleagues code your new jobs code
the same way that you did your code from
two years ago and that's such an
incredibly powerful feeling especially
if it's like well integrated into your
IDE your clone a repository open that
repository and like your testing panel
on the left hand side just populates
with all the tests and you can click on
them and run them and if an assertion
fails it's like the standard output
format that you're already familiar with
and it's a really great feeling and if
you don't believe me just go try it out
and then you will believe me
yeah no I'm totally with you I think
it's interesting because with JavaScript
in particular it feels like the default
in the community is the opposite right
there's so many different ways there are
so many different build tools and
testing Frameworks and formatters and
it's very different than like you were
mentioning a go or a Russ that are more
recent languages where they just include
that
all bundled in yeah yeah
and I think you can see this as well in
in the time that the average JavaScript
developer spends configuring their
tooling compared to a rust developer
like I write rust like all day every day
and I spend maybe
two three percent of my time configuring
rust tooling like doing dependency
Imports opening a new project creating a
formatter config file I don't know
deleting the build directory stuff like
that like that's essentially what it
means for me to configure my rust
tooling whereas if you compare this to
like a front-end JavaScript project you
have to deal with making sure that your
react version is compatible with your
react on version is compatible with your
next version is compatible with your
Veet version is compatible with your
whatever version right this is all not
automatic making sure that you use the
right as a front-ended developer you
don't have just npm installed no you
have npm installed you have yarn install
you have pnpm installed you probably
have like button installed and I don't
know to use any of these you need to
have core pack enabled and node and like
you need to have all of their global bin
directory Sim linked into your included
in your path and then if you install
something and you want to update it you
don't know did I install it with yarn
did I install it within pnpm like this
is a significant complexity and you tend
to spend a lot of time dealing with
dependencies and dealing with package
management and dealing with like tooling
configuration setting up ESL and setting
up prettier
and I think that like especially
prettier for example really showed was
one of the first things in the
JavaScript ecosystem which was like no
we're not going to give you a config
where you that you can spend like six
hours configuring it's gonna be like
seven options and here you go and
everybody used it because nobody likes
configuring things it turns out and even
though there's always the people that
say oh well I won't use your tool unless
like we get this all the time like I'm
not going to use Dino fmt because I
can't I don't know remove the semicolons
or or use single quotes or change my tab
width to 16 right like okay wait until
all of your co-workers are going to
scream at you because you set the tablet
to 16 and then see what they change it
to and then you'll see that it's
actually the exact default that
everybody uses
so it'll it'll take a couple more years
but I think we're also going to get
there like notice starting to implement
a test Runner and I think over time
we're also gonna
Converge on on on like some standard
build tools like I think Veet for
example is a great example of this like
doing a front-end project nowadays like
building new front-end tooling that's
not built on Veet yeah don't like it's
become the standard and I think we're
going to see that in a lot more places
yeah though I I Think It's Tricky right
because you have so many people with
their existing projects you have people
who are starting new projects and
they're just searching the internet for
what they should use so you're going to
have people on webpack you're going to
have people on V I guess now there's
going to be turbo pack I think is
another one that's coming there's all
these different choices right and I
think it's hard to really settle on one
I guess but yeah yeah like I think this
is in my personal opinion also failure
of the node technical steering committee
for the longest time to not decide that
yes we're going to bless this as the
standard formatter for node and this is
the standard package manager for node
and they sort of did like for example
node blessed npm is the standard package
manager for node but it didn't innovate
on npm like no the Techno technical
steering committee did not force npm to
innovate npm is a private company
ultimately bought by GitHub and they had
full control over or how the you know
npm CLI evolved and
nobody forced npm to make sure that
package install times are six times
faster than they were three years ago
like nobody did that so it didn't happen
and I think this is really a failure of
the no technical steering committee and
also the wider JavaScript ecosystem of
not being persistent enough with like
focus on performance focus on user
experience
and then focus on Simplicity like things
got so out of hand and I'm happy we're
going in the right direction now but
yeah
it was terrible for some time
so I want to talk a little bit about how
we've been talking about Dino in the
context of you just using Dino using its
own standard library but just recently
last year
you added a compatibility shim where
people are able to use node libraries in
Dino and I wonder if you could talk to
like earlier you had mentioned that Dino
has different permissions model on the
website it mentions that Dino is
standard HTTP server is two times faster
than node in a hello world example and
I'm wondering what kind of benefits
people will still get from Dino if they
choose to use packages from node yeah
it's a great question so I think again
this is sort of a like so just to
clarify what we actually implemented
like what we have is we have support for
you to import npm packages so you can
import any npm package from npm
from your typescript or JavaScript
ecmascript module that you already have
for your Gmail code
and we will under the hood make sure
that is installed somewhere in some
directory globally like pnpm does
there's no local node modules folder you
have to deal with there's no package to
Json you have to deal with and there's
no package Json like versioning things
you need to do with like what you do is
you do import
kawasay from npm colon cow say at one
and that will import cow say
with like December tag one um and it'll
like do the same resolution the same way
node does
or the same way npm does rather
and what you get from that is that
essentially it gives you like this back
door to a call out to all of the
existing node code that has been written
like you cannot expect that Dino
developers write like I don't know there
was this time when Dino did not really
have that many third-party modules yet
it was very early on and you either if
you wanted to connect to postgres and
there was no postgres driver available
then the solution was to write your own
postgres driver and that is obviously
not
great
um so the better solution here is to let
users for these packages where there's
no Dino native or web native or standard
native package for this yet that is
importable with URL specifiers you can
import this from npm so it's sort of
this like back door into the existing
npm ecosystem and we explicitly for
example don't allow you
to create a package Json file or import
bear node specifiers because we want to
stay standards compliant here but to
make this work effectively we need to
give you this little back door and
inside of this back door all hell is
like or like everything is terrible
inside there right like inside there you
can do bear specifier is it inside there
you can like there's package jsons and
there's crazy node resolution and
underscore underscore name and common JS
and like all of that stuff is supported
inside of this back door to make all the
npm packages work but on the outside
it's exposed as this nice esm only npm
specifiers and the reason you would want
to use this over like just using node
directly is because again like you want
to use typescript no config like
necessary you want to use you want to
have a formatter you want to have a
linter you want to have tooling that
like does testing and benchmarking and
compiling or whatever all that's built
in you would have run this on the edge
like close to your user isn't like 35
different points of presence it's like
okay push it to your git repository go
to this website click a button two times
and it's running in 35 data centers like
this is a kind of EX like developer
experience that you can you do not get
you I will argue that you cannot get
with node right now like even if you're
using something like TS node it is not
possible to get the same level of
developer experience that you do with
Dino the same like speed at which you
can iterate on your projects like create
new projects iterate on them is like
incredibly fast and you know like I can
open a folder on my computer create a
single file main.ts put some code in
there and then call Dino Run main.ts and
that's it like I don't I did not need to
do npm install and I did not need to do
npm init Dash Y and remove the license
and version fields from the generated
package Json and like set private to
true and whatever else right it just all
works out of the box and I think that's
what a lot of people come to jail for
and and then ultimately State Farm and
also yeah standards compliance so things
you build in Dino now are going to work
in five ten years
with no hassle and so with this
compatibility layer or this shim is it
where the node code is calling out to
node apis and you're replacing those
with Dino compatible equivalents
yeah exactly like for example we have a
shim in place that shims out the node
crypto API on top of the web crypto API
like sort of some people may be familiar
with this in the form of browserify
shims if anybody still remembers those
it's essentially your front-end tooling
you were able to import from like node
crypto in your front-end projects and
then behind the scenes your web packs or
your browser replies or whatever would
take that import from node crypto and
would replace it with like this shim
that was essentially exposed the same
API as node crypto but under the hood
wasn't implemented with Native calls but
was implemented on top of webcrypto or
implemented in user land even and you
know there's something similar there's a
couple edge cases of apis that we do not
expose the underlying thing that we shim
to to end users outside of the node shim
so like there's some apis that I don't
know if I have a good example like node
next tick for example like to properly
be able to shim node next tick you need
to like implement this within the event
Loop in the runtime
and you don't need this in Dino because
you know you use the web standard Q
micro task to do this kind of thing but
to be able to shim it correctly and run
node applications correctly we need to
have this sort of like back door into
some ugly apis which which natively
integrate in the runtime but yeah I love
this node code to run anytime you're
replacing a component with a shim I
think there's concerns about
additional bugs or changes in behavior
that can be introduced is that something
that you're seeing and how are you
accounting for that yeah it's an
excellent question so this is actually a
great concern that we have all the time
and it's not just even introducing bugs
sometimes it's removing bugs like
sometimes there's bugs in the node
standard Library which are there and
people are relying on these bugs to be
there for the applications to function
correctly we've seen this a lot and then
we implement this and we Implement from
scratch and we don't make that same bug
and then the test fails or then the
application fails so what we do is we
actually run nodes test Suite against
Dino's shim layer so node has a very
extensive test suite for its own
standard library and we can run this
Suite against against our shims to find
things like this and there's still edge
cases obviously which node like there
was maybe there's a bug which node was
not even aware of existing where maybe
this like it's now like intended
Behavior because somebody relies on it
right like the second somebody relies on
on some nonsense or some buggy Behavior
it becomes intended but maybe there was
no test that explicitly tests for this
behave Behavior so in that case we'll
add our own tests to ensure that but
overall we can already catch a lot of
these by just testing against nodes test
and then the other thing is we run a lot
of real code like we'll try run pritzma
and we'll try run Veet and we'll try run
next.js and we'll try run like I don't
know a bunch of other things that people
throw at us and check that they work and
they work and there's no bugs then
we did our job well and our ships are
implemented correctly and then there's
obviously always the edge cases where
somebody did something absolutely crazy
that nobody thought
possible and then they'll open an issue
on the dino repo and we scratch our
heads for three days then we'll fix it
and then in the next release there'll be
a new bug that we added to make the
compatibility with node better so yeah
running tests is the main thing running
nodes test
are there performance implications if
someone is running an Express app or an
xjs app and you know will they get any
benefits from the dino runtime and
performance
yeah it's actually there is performance
implications and they're usually the
opposite of what people think they are
like usually when you think of
performance implications it's always a
negative thing right so it's okay it's
like it's like a compromise like the
shimlier must be slower than the real
node right it's not like we can run
Express faster than node can run Express
and obviously not everything is faster
in Dino than it is in node and not
everything is faster node than it is a
dino it's dependent on the API dependent
on on what each team decided to optimize
and this also extends to other runtimes
like you can always cherry pick results
like I don't know to make your runtime
look faster in certain benchmarks but
overall what really matters is that you
do not the first important step for good
node compatibility is to make sure that
if somebody runs your code or runs their
node code in Dino or your other end type
or whatever it performs at least the
same and then anything on top of that
great cherry on top perfect but make
sure the bass lines is at least the same
and I think yeah we have very few apis
where like there's a significant
performance degradation in Dino compared
to node and like we're actively working
on these things like Dino is not a
project that's done right like we have I
think at this point like 15 or 16 or 17
Engineers working on Dino spanning
across all of our different projects and
like we have a whole team that's
dedicated to Performance and a whole
team that's dedicated to node
compatibility so like these things get
addressed and we make patch releases
every week and a minor release every
four weeks so yeah it's not a standstill
it's constantly improving
another thing I've seen with Dino is it
supports running webassembly minors so
you can export functions and call them
from typescript I was curious if you've
seen practical uses of this in
production
within the context of Dino yeah there's
actually a bunch of really practical use
cases so probably the most executed bit
of webassembly inside of Dino right now
is actually es build like yes build has
a webassembly build like yes build is
something to written and go you have the
choice of either running it natively in
machine code as like in elf process on
Linux or on on Windows or whatever or
you can use the webassembly build and
then it runs in webassembly and the web
assembly build is maybe 50 slower than
the native build but that is still
significantly faster than
roll up or whatever else people use
nowadays to do JavaScript bundling I
don't know I I just use yes build always
um so for example the Dina website is
running on Dino deploy and Dino deploy
does not allow you to run sub processes
because it's it's like this Edge runtime
which has certain security permissions
that it's that are not granted uh one of
them being sub processes so it needs to
execute yes build and the weight
executes es build is by running them
inside a webassembly because webassembly
is secure webassembly is is something
which is part of the JavaScript sandbox
it's inside the JavaScript sandbox it
doesn't poke any holes out
um so it's it's able to run within like
very strict security context and then
other examples are I don't know you want
to have a HTML sanitizer which is
actually built on the real HTML parser
in a browser
um like we have an HTML sanitizer called
comrade or ammonia I don't remember
there's an HTML sanitizer library on
digital land X which is built on the
HTML parser from Firefox which like
ensures essentially that your HTML like
if you do HTML sanitization you need to
make sure your HTML parse is correct
because if it's not your browser might
parse some HTML one way and your
sanitizer applies it another way and
then it doesn't sanitize everything
correctly so there's like the Firefox
HTML parser compile to webassembly you
can use that to do HTML sanitization or
the dino documentation generation tool
for example Arduino dock there's a
webassembly built for it that allows you
to programmatically like generate
documentation for your typescript
modules and and also like Dino fmt is
available as a webassembly module for
programmatic Access and a bunch of other
internal genome programs as well like
components not programs what are some of
the current limitations of webassembly
and Dino for example from webassembly
can I make HTTP requests can I read
files that sort of thing yeah so
webassembly like when you spawn a
webassembly they're called instances web
zombie instances it runs inside of the
same VM like the same V8 isolate is what
they're called but
it's like a completely fresh sandbox
sort of in the sense that I told you
that between a run time and like an
engine essentially implements no I O
calls right and runtime does like a
runtime pokes holds into the engine web
assembly by default works the same way
that there's no holes poked into its
sandbox so you have to explicitly poke
some holes if you want to do HTTP calls
for example when you create the
webassembly instance it gives you or you
can give it something called Imports
which are essentially JavaScript
function bindings which you can call
from within the webassembly and you can
use those function bindings to do
anything you can from JavaScript you
just have to pass them through
explicitly and yeah depending on how you
write your webassembly like if you write
it in Rust for example the tooling is
very nice and you can just call some
JavaScript code from your rust and then
the build system will automatically make
sure that the right function bindings
are passed through with the right names
and like you don't have to deal with
anything and if you're writing go it's
slightly more complicated and if you're
writing like raw web assembly like the
web assembly text format and compiling
that to a binary then you have to do
everything yourself right it's sort of
the difference between writing C and
writing JavaScript like what level of
abstraction do you want it's definitely
possible though and that's for
limitations the same limitations as
exist in Bowser's apply like the
webassembly support in Dino is
equivalent to the webassembly supporting
Chrome so you can do many things like
multi-threading and stuff like that
already but especially around like
shared mutable memory and having access
to that memory from JavaScript that's
something which is a real difficulty
with webassembly right now yeah growing
webassembly memory is also rather
difficult right now there's there's a
there's a couple inherent limitations
right now with webassembly itself but
those will be worked out over time and
and Dino is like very up to date with
the version of the standard it
implements through V8 we're up to date
with Chrome Beta essentially all the
time so yeah anything you see in Chrome
Beta is going to be in dino already so
you talked a little bit about this
before the dino team they have their own
hosting platform called Dino deploy so I
wonder if you could explain
what that is yeah so Dino has this
really nice this really nice concept of
permissions which allow you to sorry I'm
going to start somewhere slightly
unrelated maybe it sounds like it's
unrelated but you'll see in a second
it's not unrelated Dino has this really
nice permission system which allows you
to sandbox Dino programs to only allow
them to do certain operations for
example in you know by default if you
try to open a file it'll air out and say
you don't have read permissions to read
this file and then what you do is you
specify dash dash allow read and maybe
you have to give it you can either
specify that read and then it'll Grant
to read access to the entire file system
or you can explicitly specify files or
folders or any number of things same
goes for write permissions same goes for
Network permissions same goes for
running sub processes all these kind of
things
and by limiting your permissions just a
little bit like for example by just
disabling sub-processes and foreign
function interface but allowing
everything else allowing reads and
allowing network access and all that
kind of stuff we can run Dino programs
in a way that is significantly more cost
effective to you as the end user than
and like we can cold start them much
faster than like you may be able to with
a more conventional container based
system so what you need to deploy is is
a way to run JavaScript or Dino code on
our data centers all across the world
with very little latency like you can
write some JavaScript code which serves
HTTP requests deploy that to our
platform and then we'll make sure to
spin that code up all across the world
and have your users be able to access it
through some URL or some custom domain
or something like that and this is very
similar to cloudflare workers for
example and it's like netlify Edge
functions is built on top of Dino deploy
like netlify Edge functions is in
implemented on top of Geno deploy
through our sub hosting product yeah
essentially you know deploy is a cloud
hosting service for JavaScript which
allows you to execute arbitrary
JavaScript
and there's a couple like different
directions we're going there one is like
more end user focused where like you
link your GitHub repository and like
we'll have a nice experience like you do
with netlify and versel that word like
your commits automatically get deployed
and you get preview deployments and all
that kind of thing for your backend code
though rather than for your front-end
websites although you could also write
front-ended websites if you know
obviously and the other direction is
more like business focused like you're
writing a SAS application and you want
to allow the user to customize the check
like you're writing a SAS application
that provides users with the ability to
write their own online store and you
want to give them some ability to
customize the checkout experience in
some way so you give them a little like
text editor that they can type some
JavaScript into and then when your SAS
application needs to hit this code path
it sends a request to us with the code
we'll execute that code for you in a
secure way in a secure sandbox you can
like tell us this code only has access
to like my API server and no other
networks to like prevent data
exfiltration for example and then you
can have all this like super
customizable code in inside of your your
SAS application without having to deal
with any of the operational complexities
of scaling arbitrary code execution or
even just doing arbitrary code execution
right like this is a very difficult
problem and give it to someone else and
we deal with it and you just get the
benefits
that's you know to play and it's built
by the same team that builds the dino
CLI so all of your favorite like you
know CLI or Dino apis are available in
there it's
just as web standard is Dino like you
have fetch available you have blob
available you have crypto available that
kind of thing so when someone ships you
their code and you run it you mentioned
that the cold start time is very low how
is
the code being run are people getting
their own process it sounds like it's
not using containers I wonder if you
could explain a little bit about how
that works
yeah I can I can revive the overview of
hard work so the way it works is that we
essentially have a pool of Dino
processes well it's not quite Dino it's
not the same Dino CLI that you download
it's like a modified version of the dino
CLI based on the same infrastructure
that we have spun up across all of our
different regions across the world
across all over different data centers
and then when we get a request we'll
route that request the first time we get
a request for that we call them
deployments that like code right we'll
take one of these Idol Dino processes
and we'll assign that code to run in
that process and then that process can
go serve the requests and these process
they're isolated and they're it's
essentially a V8 isolate and it's a very
very slim it's a much much Slimmer
version of the dino CLI essentially
which the only thing it can do is
Javascript execution and like it can't
even execute typescript for example like
typescript is we pre-process it up front
to make the cold start faster and then
what we do is if you don't get quest for
some amount of time will spin down that
isolate and we'll spin up a new idle one
in its place and then if you get another
request an hour later for that same
deployment we'll assign it to a new
isolate and yeah that's a cold start
right if you have an isolate which
receives or a deployment rather which
receives a bunch of traffic like let's
say you receive 100 requests per second
we can send a bunch of that traffic to
the same isolate and we'll make sure
that if that one isolate isn't able to
handle that load we'll spin it out over
multiple isolates and we'll sort of load
balance for you and we'll make sure to
always send to the point of presence
that's closest to the user making the
request so they get very minimal latency
we have these like layers of load
balancing in place and I'm glossing over
a bunch of like security related things
here about how these these processes are
actually isolated and how we monitor to
ensure that you don't break out of these
processes and for example Dino deployed
does it looks like you have a file
system because you can read files from
the file system but in reality Dino
deploy does not have a file system the
file system is a global virtual file
system which is yeah implemented
completely differently than it is in
Dino CLI but as an end user you don't
have to care about that because the only
thing you care about is that it has the
exact same API as the dino CLI and you
can run your code locally and if it
works there it's also going to work in
deploy
so that's kind of a high level of do no
deploy if any of this sounds interesting
to anyone by the way we're like very
actively hiring on Dino deploy I happen
to be the tech lead for you know deploy
product so I'm I'm always looking for
engineers to join RX and build cool
distributed systems at dino.com jobs for
people who aren't familiar with the
isolates are these each run in their own
processes or do you have a single
process and that has a whole bunch of
isolates inside them
so we run most isolates in a single in
the general case you can say that we run
one isolator process
but
there is
many asterisks on that because it's very
complicated I'll just say it's very
complicated in the general case though
it's one I slip for process yeah one of
the things you mentioned about dno
deploy is it's centered around deploying
your application code to a bunch of
different locations and you also
mentioned the cold start times very low
could you kind of give the case for
wanting your application code at a bunch
of different sites yeah so the main
benefit of this is that when your user
makes a request your application you
don't have to round trip back to
wherever centrally hosted your
application would otherwise be like if
you are a startup even if you're just in
the US for example it's nice to have
points of presence not just on one of
the US coasts but on both of the U.S
coasts because that means that your
round trip time is not going to be 100
milliseconds but it's going to be 20
milliseconds this sort of relies on
there's obviously always the problem
here that if your database lives in only
one of the two coasts you still need to
do the round trip and there's solutions
to this which is one caching that's the
obvious sort of boring solution and then
there's the solution of using databases
which are built exactly for this for
example cockroachdb is a database which
is postgres compatible but it's really
built for global distribution and built
for being able to Shard data across
regions and have different primary
regions for different shards of your
tables which means for example you could
have your users on the East Coast their
data could live on a database in the
east coast and your users on the west
coast their data could live on a
database in the west coast and your like
admin panel needs to show all of them as
an aggregate view over both coasts right
like this is something which which
something like cockroach TV can do and
it can be a really great thing here and
we acknowledge that this is not
something which is very easy to do right
now and Dino tries to make everything
very easy so you can imagine that where
this is something we're working on and
we're working on database Solutions and
actually I should more generally say
persistent solutions that allow you to
persist data in a way that makes sense
for an edge system like this where the
data is persisted close to users that
need it and data is cached around the
world and you still have sort of
semantics which are consistent with the
semantics that you have when you're
locally developing applications like you
don't want for example your local
application development you don't want
there to be like strong consistency
there but then in production you have
eventual consistency where suddenly I
don't know all of your code breaks
because you didn't your U.S West Region
didn't pick up the changes from U.S east
because it's eventually consistent right
I mean this is a problem that we see
with a lot of the existing Solutions
here like specifically Cloud KV for
example cloudflare KV is a single
primary is a system with single primary
right regions where there's just a bunch
of caching going on and this leads to
eventual consistency which can be very
confusing for end user developers
especially because
if you're using this locally the local
emulator does not emulate the eventual
consistency right so this can become
very confusing very quickly and so
anything that we build in this
persistence field for example we very
seriously weigh these trade-offs and
make sure that if there's something
that's eventually consistent it's very
clear and it works the same way the same
eventually consistent way in the CLI so
for someone let's say they haven't made
that jump yet to use a cockroach they
just have their database instance in AWS
East or whatever
does having the code at the edge where
it all ends up needing to go to East is
that
actually
better than having the code be located
next to the database
yeah yeah it totally does there's
trade-offs here right obviously if you
have an admin panel for example or a
like user dashboard which is very very
reliant on data from your database and
for every single request needs to fetch
fresh data from the database then maybe
the trade-off isn't worth it but most
applications are not like that most
applications are for example you have a
landing page and that landing page needs
to do a b tests and those a b tests are
based on some heuristic that you can
fetch from the database every five
seconds that's fine like it doesn't need
to be perfect right so you have caching
in place which like by doing this
caching locally to the user and still
being able to programmatically control
this like based on I don't know the
user's user agent or the IP address of
the user or the region of the user or
the past browsing history of that user
as measured by their cookies or whatever
else right being able to do these highly
user customized actions very close to
the user means that like latency is like
this is a much better experience than if
you have to do the round trip especially
if you're a startup or a service which
is globally distributed and serves not
just users in the US or the EU but like
all across the world and when you talk
about caching in the context of Dino
deploy is there a cash native to the
system or are you expecting someone to
have a redis or a memcache that sort of
thing yeah so do you know deploy
actually has there's a web cache API
which is also the webcast API that's
used by service workers and and others
and cloudflare also influence this cache
API and this is something that's
implemented in Dino CLI and it's going
to be coming to you know deploy this
quarter which is that's the native way
to do caching and otherwise you can also
use reddits you can use services like
upstash or even like primitive in-memory
caches where it's just an lru that's in
memory like a JavaScript data structure
right or even just a JavaScript map or
JavaScript object with a Time on it and
you automatically and like every time
you read from it and the time is above
some certain threshold you delete the
cache and go fetch it again right like
this is there's many things that you
could consider a cache that are not like
redis or like the web cache API so
there's ways to do that and there's also
a bunch of like modules on in the
standard library or not in the standard
Library sorry in the third party module
registry and also on npm that you can
use to implement different cache
behaviors
and when you give the example of a
in-memory cache when you're running in
Dino deploy you're running in these
isolates which presumably can be shut
down at any time so what kind of
guarantees do
users have that whatever they put into
memory will still be there none like
it's a cache right the Cache can be
evicted at any time your isolate can be
restarted at any time it can be shut
down you can be moved to a different
region the data center could go down for
maintenance like this is something your
application has to be built in in a way
that it is tolerant to restarts
essentially but because it's a cache
that's fine because if the cache expires
or the cash is cleared through some
external means the worst thing that
happens is that you have a cold request
again right and if you're serving like
100 requests a second I can essentially
guarantee to you that not every single
request will invoke a cold start like I
can guarantee to you that probably less
than 0.1 percent of requests will cause
a cold start this is not like sl8
anywhere because it's like totally up to
however the system decides to scale you
but yeah like it would be very wasteful
for us for example to spin up a new
isolate for every request so we don't
reuse isolates wherever possible it's an
our best interest to not cold start you
because it's expensive for us to do all
the CPU work to cold start nice Lorraine
and if I understand correctly Dino
deploy it's centered around applications
that take HTTP requests so it could be a
website it could be an API that sort of
thing and sometimes when people build
applications they have other things
surrounding them they'll need scheduled
jobs they may need some form of message
queue things like that things that don't
necessarily fit into what Dino to play
currently hosts and so I wonder for
things like that what you recommend
people would do while working with Dino
deploy great question unfortunately I
can't tell you too much about that
without like spoiling everything
but what I'm gonna say is you should
keep your eyes peeled on our blog over
the next two to three months here I
consider message cues and like
especially message cues they are a
persistence feature and we are currently
working on persistence features so yeah
that's all I'm going to say but you can
expect you know deploy to do things
other than just HTTP requests in the not
so far future
and like crime jobs and stuff like that
also at some point yeah all right we'll
look out for that
I guess as we wrap up maybe you could
give some examples of who's using Dino
and what types of projects do you think
are ideal for Dino yeah like do you know
as in all of Dino or Dino deployment I
mean I guess either either or but yeah
yeah okay yeah yeah let's do it so one
really cool use case for example for
Dino is slack slack has this app
platform that they're building which
allows you to execute arbitrary
JavaScript from with inside of slack in
response to like slash commands and like
actions I don't know if you've ever seen
like those little buttons you can have
in messages if you press one of those
buttons like that can execute some dino
code and slack has built like this
entire platform around that and it makes
use of Dino's like security features and
and built-in tooling and all that kind
of thing and that's really cool and
netlify has built Edge functions like
which is like a really really awesome
primitive they have have for being able
to customize outgoing requests to even
come up with completely new requests on
the spot as part of their CDN layer also
built on top of Dino and GitHub has
built like this platform called Flat
which allows you to like sort of on
Chron schedules like pull data into git
repositories and process that and
post-process that and do things with
that and it's integrated with GitHub
action it's not kind of thing it's kind
of cool Super Bass also has some Edge
has like an edge functions product
that's built on top of Dino
a bunch of cool things like that we have
like a really active Discord Channel and
there's always people showcasing what
kind of stuff they built in there that
we have a showcase Channel I think
that's like if you're really interested
in what cool things people are building
with you know that's like that's a great
place to look I think actually maybe
also have a showcase
dino.com showcase
which is a page of like a bunch of yeah
projects built with Dino or or more
products using Dino or other things like
that cool if people want to learn more
about Dino or see what you're up to
where should they head yeah if you want
to learn more about you know CLI head to
dino.land if you want to learn more
about Dino deploy head to dino.com
deploy if you want to chat to me or you
can hit me up on my website lcast.dev if
you want to chat about Dino you can go
to discord.tg dino yeah and if you're
interested in any of this and thought
that maybe you have something to
contribute here you can either become an
open source contributor on our open
source projects or if this is really
something you want to work on and you
like distributed systems or systems
engineering or fast performance head to
gmail.com jobs and send in your resume
we're very actively hiring and be super
excited to work with you
all right Luca well thank you so much
for coming on software engineering radio
thank you so much for having me cool
this says spin Jeremy Jung for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this in all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening